Hi and welcome again to the channel.
This is a special screencast because this is the last one
until the release of the new Padre on Strawberry Windows installer.
Originally when I started this, I didn't know what was going to happen
but last month I decided that I was going to release this package once a month
but because of some exciting new features that came up
I decided that I can't wait anymore
so I wanted to release it, so here it is and you can start downloading and start using it.
I would like to show you now a couple of things that are new in this distribution.
So you can see whether it is interesting for you as well to try it out.
First of all, how to get the distribution.
So you can go to the website of Padre, padre.perlide.org
and then on the main page you have all this promotional text
but you are probably not interested because you are already convinced that you want it
so you click on the download link and here are some more text
about what kind of packages and modules are already included.
There's the release notes, whatever, you don't care about it.
what's important for you is this link where you can click on that link
and then you can download the actual distribution, the installer.
It's pretty big, it's 75 megabytes, but it contains quite a lot of things.
So once you download it and you click several times and install
and everything that you usually do in Windows
you can go to the Start menu, All programs, and then you will have a Strawberry Perl menu item
probably, depending on what you picked
and here inside you will see lots of lots of new icons.
Now this is not new for those who are using standard Strawberry Perl
but in the previous version of Padre Strawberry
we didn't have all these icons, so they are new.
And there are some icons that are actually quite new for everyone
especially the games subdirectory. So, in there, you will have three icons.
The main one here is the link to the website of the SDL Perl.
That's the technology that the games are written in.
And here is the Frozen Bubble. Frozen Bubble is the well known game which was originally written in Perl
and this is actually the original code, a newer version of it
and, oh yeah, it's starting to play.
As you can see and hear, you can press Enter here, and another Enter
and probably all kinds of things to change
and here you move with the arrows and then hit these balls and fall down and that's a great game.
I'm a really good player, almost. Yeah, I'm quite good, you see? Yeah. Hmm, next level.
So I could play here quite a long time and you would probably enjoy it very much
but I think I would like to show something else, so I quit this game. Okay, bye-bye.
Yeah. So, I quit this game and I would like to show you another one, another game.
The other game is here as well. It's called Zumbis, which is a game.
You are this red-head girl and there are zombies running after you
and you have to shoot them down or they will eat you.
The fun part is, oh, so, yeah, they eat me.
Besides the fact that you a red-head girl and zombies are after you
it's actually written in Portugese.
So, you will have to deal with that.
But, I think after zombies it's going to be okay for you.
Now, quitting the game is another adventure
because you can't just press Escape, it doesn't work
you have to press Enter to restart a game
and then you can press Escape and then it quits.
So, that's got to be fun for everyone.
And if you really want to make changes, then it's open source
so you can go to the Github repository, and start fixing it, and well, who knows what?
Who knows what?
You might have a really great game at one point. Maybe she can speak in English
or Hungarian, or whatever.
So what else is there?
As I mentioned, there is an interesting feature of Padre.
So Padre is going to be released a new version
0.86 is going to be released quite soon, in a couple of days
and it will have a new feature that's extremely surprising for anyone
who's using Perl in the last four years
because so far that was the major issue of Padre
that we didn't have correct syntax highlighting for the defined or that came out in 5.10.
And, the reason is because we were using the Scintilla editor,and the highlighter in there
and because we were using a really old version of it
a long story, it's through the WX bindings and so on, so, because of that
we didn't have correct syntax highlighting.
Now lately, Ahmad Zawawi made some heroic work and he ported, actually
created a binding directly to Scintilla.
It's called wxScintilla in Perl, and made some changes to Perl
to Padre that will come out in 0.86 that will allow you to use it.
Now, because it's not released yet, I decided because it's an important feature
I decided, I backported it, and I put it back into the 0.86, 0.84 release of Padre
and it has never been released to the publicity, only to the repository
but it's actually included in this distribution.
So, in the coming days, if you want to try this
this is the only way you can do it.
So, go ahead and download it. Now, how does it work?
You launch Padre, and once you have the desk drawer open
you open some Perl scripts. So, for example, in the examples directory
let's open this script.
I'm not really interested in the actual, what's in there
what I would like to write is this defined or.
Which, as you can see, the highlighting
I hope you can see, the highlighting is really broken.
So this is black, and then it's red
it doesn't recognize that we are talking about a defined or variable.
So, we have to enable the Scintilla, new Scintilla highlighter.
The way to do it is to go to the tools menu
preferences
we don't have a checkbox for this here, as far as I know
so we go to the advanced options
there, we then type in "Scintilla"
we start to type in
and then we hit, here is the menu option.
And as you can see it's False, so by default it doesn't, it's not used.
I turn it on, setting it true, save it, and then, it still now doesn't work
because you need to restart Padre in order for this specific feature to take effect.
So I close Padre, and start it again in the same way, and once it opens
I hate this feature, that it doesn't remember the correct
the same file that was opened already
so I go to recent files, and then I open that file
and as you can see, here is already doing the syntax highlighting correctly.
By the way, if you also hate this, that Padre doesn't open the last file that was open before you closed it
you can go to the tools
preferences, again,
and here there is the opening files entry
and here we are, that's what it says.
So we open a new file every time when you open Padre, but you can say
set it to last, which will open the last files that have been opened
or there is also session management that I don't want to go into this now
because that's not what we are talking about.
Anyway, that's a really nice feature of Padre now
that it can actually do correct syntax highlighting.
So, welcome to Perl 5.10!
That's great.
So what else?
There are a couple of other features - let's go back to this website
because it has explanations of what kinds of things are new
let's go to the release notes so I can remember, ooh yes, so
CPAN::Reporter. CPAN::Reporter
and this module which I can't read out are tools
one of the set of the tools to allow you to report
to send out test reports, to CPAN testers.
So, this website, probably you know, this is the CPAN Testers Reports website.
There are people who install CPAN modules and decide to send out reports.
The reports are collected in this place and then you can see them, and it's great.
So, in order to turn this on, you have to install various modules.
These are already coming in this distribution.
And, you have to configure it so it will send out, in your, it will be turned on
and it will be sent out in your name.
So if you go to the cpantesters.org website
and scroll down
then there is a part called "Become a tester", which links to the wiki
and they...I don't go into the details now, that's going to be a seperate screencast, probably
but you can go there and read how to set it up and then you can start sending out test reports
which is great, thanks.
What else?
Oh yeah, so
Text::CSV_XS just reads a, read or writes CSV files
and Net::Telnet, just in case you want to connect to an unsecure Unix machine.
Or, there are all these routers and bridges and whatnot
that you can configure them by a telnet interface.
And, in many times, you'll need to use them for testing or to configure these devices
so Net::Telnet is a great module for that.
App::cpanoutdated allows me to, actually, check
which modules need to be updated for the next version of this package,
but it can be used by anyone, it's a commandline tool
that will show you which modules are outdated in your installation.
Template::Toolkit, Template::Toolkit, will help me write, or anyone, actually
will help write a more complex application, web applications
Dancer, that one has been included in the earlier version.
Actually it was upgraded in this version.
But Dancer comes with a really simple template tool
template system that doesn't even have loops and stuff like this.
And now that you have Template::Toolkit installed
it's quite easy to start building complex web applications on this distribution.
Win32::GuiTest:
That's a nice module to allow you to write all kinds of automation, for desktop applications
so it allows you to click or use the mouse or drag the mouse
and, automatically obviously, without you touching the mouse
or clicking on the keyboards
and, you can automate tasks, it can be used for testing
or for automatic installations, or for stuff like this.
And then, as I mentioned, there is SDL, these are the games
and there are a couple of games that were installed.
A couple of modules have been upgraded and that's it basically.
So, I really hope that some of you will try it out
download it and try it and provide feedback.
How is the new distribution?
I really hope there aren't too many new bugs in there.
And I hope you enjoyed this screecast
and, see you next time!